Fatma Elsafoury

9 Crown Gardens, Hyndland Glasgow, UK G12 9HL 0447397955946 e.fatma.e@gmail.com

I'm a perseverant, hard working and independent researcher who is interested in applying my research skills in Machine Learning (ML) and Natural Language Processing (NLP) to analysing and detecting violence (verbal or physical) from social media. I've good communication skills that allow me to cooperate with my research team, sharing my knowledge and learning from them. I'm looking forward to working with a research team that gives me the chance to enhance my experience and develop new ways to use ML and NLP to help humanity. My research goal at the moment is to enhance my academic paper writing skills and publish more papers.

Education

2018 - 2019 MSc in Computing Science

Glasgow university, The UK Submitting the 30th of May 2019

Funded by: Lord Kelvin Adam Smith (LKAS).

Thesis Title: Detecting protest repression incidents from tweets.

Description: I use Machine-learning models, Natural Language Processing to detect incidents of violence done by the state against the protestors from tweets. I use the Gezi park protest in Turkey 2013 as a case study. Then I do word analysis and time line analysis on the labelled tweets.

Tools: I use mainly Python packages like NLTK, Sklearn, Tensorflow, Pandas, Matplotlib

and Numpy.

2011 - 2013 MSc in Geo-Informatics

University of Twente, Overijsle state, The Netherlands

Thesis Title: Monitoring Urban Traffic Status Using Twitter Messages.

Scholarship: Erasmus Munds.

Grade: Good.

2004 - 2008 BSc Computer Science

Helwan University, Cairo, Egypt

Dissertation Project: Iris Recognition System.

Grade: Very Good.

Experience

April 2019 - Now Data Science Lecturer (Part-Time)

School of computing science

Dundee university

Responsibilities:

- Helping students with Machine learning assignments
- Marking assignments
- Supervising 4 MSc students.

2014 - 2018 Research Assistant

School of computing science

Glasgow university

Project Title: Measuring electoral and protest violence from tweets

The project is interdisciplinary project between computing science school and school of political science. We worked on detecting violence in tweets during elections and during protests. We also worked on detecting fraud during the Scottish referendum 2014. Worked with Tweets from Venezuela elections 2015, Indian elections 2016 and Turkish Gezi protest 2013.

Responsibilities:

- Pre-processing data
- Create Machine learning models
- Analyse model's performance
- Labelling data
- Designing and conducting crowdsourcing experiments
- Writing reports
- · Wrote my MSc thesis as part of the project

2017 - 2018 Teaching Assistant

Computing Science school Glasgow University

Responsibilities:

- Tutoring Python and Java.
- Supervised 2 MSc students on their dissertations.
- Exams invigilation.
- Marking.

2018 **Python Tutor (Volunteer)**

Programming workshop

School of Math

Ibadan University, Nigeria

Responsibilities:

- Preparing course material.
- Teaching Python (Basics).
- Teaching Data science toolkit (Pandas, Numpy and MatplotLib).

.

2018 Web development Instructor (Volunteer)

Code For girls Glasgow University

Responsibilities:

- Teaching HTML, CSS, JavaScript, Bootstrap and JQuery.
- Teaching GitHub.

Experience (Working)

2013 - 2014 GIS software developer

ESRI NEA, Egypt.

Role: Responsible of developing web-mapping applications using Java script, ArcGIS web.

2009 - 2011 GIS software developer

ICON Technologies, Egypt.

Role: Responsible of designing and developing GIS web and desktop applications using C#, ASP.net and ArcGIS.

Publications

2017 Birch S, Elsafoury F. Fraud, plot, or collective delusion? Social media

and perceptions of electoral misconduct in the 2014 scottish

independence referendum. Election Law Journal: Rules, Politics, and

Policy. 2017 Dec 1;16(4):470-484. Available from,

DOI: 10.1089/elj.2016.0393

2013 Elsafoury FA. Monitoring urban traffic status using Twitter messages.

University of Twente Faculty of Geo-Information and Earth Observation

(ITC); 2013 Feb.

Personal Information

Achievements I'm proud to have done the following achievements:

 Winning Erasmus Munds scholarship 2011. One of only 3 women from Egypt who got accepted in the Netherlands.

- Winning LKAS scholarship 2014. One of only 11 students who got this scholarship for 2014. The only student from Egypt, Africa and the Middle East for 2014.
- Participation in staring a mental health first aide group for PhD students in Glasgow University 2018.
- Volunteering for teaching Python to undergraduate students in Ibadan University, Nigeria 2018.
- Volunteering for teaching basic web technologies to women in Glasgow University, UK 2018.

LinkedIn https://www.linkedin.com/in/fatma-elsafoury-64390a20/

Github https://github.com/efatmae

Languages Arabic (Native)

English (Fluent) French (Basics)

Interests I love learning new things all the time. This is why over that last four years

I did a film making class, skating class, cycling class, swimming classes, squash lessons, Pottery class, Guitar class, Portrait and oil painting

classes. Tou can find some of my artwork on Instgram.

https://www.instagram.com/e.fatma.e/